<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<RelativeLayout
    xmlns:android="http://schemas.android.com/apk/res/android"
    android:layout_width="match_parent"
    android:layout_height="match_parent"
    >

    <TextView
        android:layout_width="match_parent"
        android:layout_height="wrap_content"
        android:gravity="center"
        android:fontFamily="serif"
        android:textStyle="bold"
        android:text="Generic, Traits, Lifetimes"
        android:textColor="@color/black"
        android:textSize="35dp"
        android:id="@+id/headingch10"/>


    <ScrollView xmlns:android="http://schemas.android.com/apk/res/android"
        android:layout_width="match_parent"
        android:layout_height="match_parent"
        android:fillViewport="true"
        android:layout_below="@id/headingch10">

        <LinearLayout
            android:layout_margin="4dp"
            android:orientation="vertical"
            android:layout_width="match_parent"
            android:layout_height="wrap_content">



            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="23sp"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:id="@+id/tfc2"
                android:text="   Every programming language has tools for effectively handling the duplication of concepts. In Rust, one such tool is generics. Generics are abstract stand-ins for concrete types or other properties. When we’re writing code, we can express the behavior of generics or how they relate to other generics without knowing what will be in their place when compiling and running the code.

Similar to the way a function takes parameters with unknown values to run the same code on multiple concrete values, functions can take parameters of some generic type instead of a concrete type, like i32 or String. In fact, we’ve already used generics in Chapter 6 with Option T, Chapter 8 with VecT  and HashMap K, V , and Chapter 9 with Result T, E. In this chapter, you’ll explore how to define your own types, functions, and methods with generics!

First, we’ll review how to extract a function to reduce code duplication. Next, we’ll use the same technique to make a generic function from two functions that differ only in the types of their parameters. We’ll also explain how to use generic types in struct and enum definitions.

Then you’ll learn how to use traits to define behavior in a generic way. You can combine traits with generic types to constrain a generic type to only those types that have a particular behavior, as opposed to just any type.

Finally, we’ll discuss lifetimes, a variety of generics that give the compiler information about how references relate to each other. Lifetimes allow us to borrow values in many situations while still enabling the compiler to check that the references are valid."/>


            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="25sp"
                android:fontFamily="serif"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="Generic Data Types"/>

            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="25sp"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="   We can use generics to create definitions for items like function signatures or structs, which we can then use with many different concrete data types. Let’s first look at how to define functions, structs, enums, and methods using generics. Then we’ll discuss how generics affect code performance.

In Function Definitions
When defining a function that uses generics, we place the generics in the signature of the function where we would usually specify the data types of the parameters and return value. Doing so makes our code more flexible and provides more functionality to callers of our function while preventing code duplication.The largest_i32 function is the one we extracted in Listing 10-3 that finds the largest i32 in a slice. The largest_char function finds the largest char in a slice. The function bodies have the same code, so let’s eliminate the duplication by introducing a generic type parameter in a single function.

To parameterize the types in the new function we’ll define, we need to name the type parameter, just as we do for the value parameters to a function. You can use any identifier as a type parameter name. But we’ll use T because, by convention, parameter names in Rust are short, often just a letter, and Rust’s type-naming convention is CamelCase. Short for “type,” T is the default choice of most Rust programmers.

When we use a parameter in the body of the function, we have to declare the parameter name in the signature so the compiler knows what that name means. Similarly, when we use a type parameter name in a function signature, we have to declare the type parameter name before we use it."/>



            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="25sp"
                android:fontFamily="serif"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="In Struct Definitions"/>

            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="23sp"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="   We can also define structs to use a generic type parameter in one or more fields using the sign of greater than less than, syntax.The syntax for using generics in struct definitions is similar to that used in function definitions. First, we declare the name of the type parameter inside angle brackets just after the name of the struct. Then we can use the generic type in the struct definition where we would otherwise specify concrete data types.

Note that because we’ve used only one generic type to define Point T In between the sign of greater than less than, this definition says that the Point T struct is generic over some type T, and the fields x and y are both that same type, whatever that type may be. If we create an instance of a Point T that has values of different types."/>

            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="25sp"
                android:fontFamily="serif"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="Performance of Code Using Generics"/>
            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textSize="23sp"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="   You might be wondering whether there is a runtime cost when you’re using generic type parameters. The good news is that Rust implements generics in such a way that your code doesn’t run any slower using generic types than it would with concrete types.
Rust accomplishes this by performing monomorphization of the code that is using generics at compile time. Monomorphization is the process of turning generic code into specific code by filling in the concrete types that are used when compiled.
In this process, the compiler does the opposite of the steps we used to create the generic function in Listing 10-5: the compiler looks at all the places where generic code is called and generates code for the concrete types the generic code is called with.When Rust compiles this code, it performs monomorphization. During that process, the compiler reads the values that have been used in Option T instances and identifies two kinds of Option T: one is i32 and the other is f64. As such, it expands the generic definition of Option T into Option_i32 and Option_f64, thereby replacing the generic definition with the specific ones.  Because Rust compiles generic code into code that specifies the type in each instance, we pay no runtime cost for using generics. When the code runs, it performs just as it would if we had duplicated each definition by hand. The process of monomorphization makes Rust’s generics extremely efficient at runtime."/>

            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="25sp"
                android:fontFamily="serif"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="Traits: Defining Shared Behavior"/>
            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="23sp"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="   A trait tells the Rust compiler about functionality a particular type has and can share with other types. We can use traits to define shared behavior in an abstract way. We can use trait bounds to specify that a generic can be any type that has certain behavior."/>


            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="25sp"
                android:fontFamily="serif"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="Defining a Trait"/>
            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="23sp"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="   Defining a Trait
A type’s behavior consists of the methods we can call on that type. Different types share the same behavior if we can call the same methods on all of those types. Trait definitions are a way to group method signatures together to define a set of behaviors necessary to accomplish some purpose.

For example, let’s say we have multiple structs that hold various kinds and amounts of text: a NewsArticle struct that holds a news story filed in a particular location and a Tweet that can have at most 280 characters along with metadata that indicates whether it was a new tweet, a retweet, or a reply to another tweet.

We want to make a media aggregator library that can display summaries of data that might be stored in a NewsArticle or Tweet instance. To do this, we need a summary from each type, and we need to request that summary by calling a summarize method on an instance. Here, we declare a trait using the trait keyword and then the trait’s name, which is Summary in this case. Inside the curly brackets, we declare the method signatures that describe the behaviors of the types that implement this trait, which in this case is fn summarize(ampersand sign self) -> String.

After the method signature, instead of providing an implementation within curly brackets, we use a semicolon. Each type implementing this trait must provide its own custom behavior for the body of the method. The compiler will enforce that any type that has the Summary trait will have the method summarize defined with this signature exactly. A trait can have multiple methods in its body: the method signatures are listed one per line and each line ends in a semicolon."/>

            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="25sp"
                android:fontFamily="serif"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="Using Trait Bounds to Conditionally Implement Methods"/>
            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="23sp"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="   We can also conditionally implement a trait for any type that implements another trait. Implementations of a trait on any type that satisfies the trait bounds are called blanket implementations and are extensively used in the Rust standard library. For example, the standard library implements the ToString trait on any type that implements the Display trait.Traits and trait bounds let us write code that uses generic type parameters to reduce duplication but also specify to the compiler that we want the generic type to have particular behavior. The compiler can then use the trait bound information to check that all the concrete types used with our code provide the correct behavior. In dynamically typed languages, we would get an error at runtime if we called a method on a type which didn’t define the method. But Rust moves these errors to compile time so we’re forced to fix the problems before our code is even able to run. Additionally, we don’t have to write code that checks for behavior at runtime because we’ve already checked at compile time. Doing so improves performance without having to give up the flexibility of generics.

Another kind of generic that we’ve already been using is called lifetimes. Rather than ensuring that a type has the behavior we want, lifetimes ensure that references are valid as long as we need them to be. Let’s look at how lifetimes do that."/>




            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="25sp"
                android:fontFamily="serif"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="Validating References with Lifetimes"/>
            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="23sp"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="   One detail we didn’t discuss in the “References and Borrowing” section in Chapter 4 is that every reference in Rust has a lifetime, which is the scope for which that reference is valid. Most of the time, lifetimes are implicit and inferred, just like most of the time, types are inferred. We must annotate types when multiple types are possible. In a similar way, we must annotate lifetimes when the lifetimes of references could be related in a few different ways. Rust requires us to annotate the relationships using generic lifetime parameters to ensure the actual references used at runtime will definitely be valid.

The concept of lifetimes is somewhat different from tools in other programming languages, arguably making lifetimes Rust’s most distinctive feature. Although we won’t cover lifetimes in their entirety in this chapter, we’ll discuss common ways you might encounter lifetime syntax so you can become familiar with the concepts."/>






            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="25sp"
                android:fontFamily="serif"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="Lifetime Annotation syntax"/>
            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="23sp"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="   Now let’s examine lifetime annotations in the context of the longest function. As with generic type parameters, we need to declare generic lifetime parameters inside angle brackets between the function name and the parameter list. The constraint we want to express in this signature is that all the references in the parameters and the return value must have the same lifetime. We’ll name the lifetime 'a and then add it to each reference.The function signature now tells Rust that for some lifetime 'a, the function takes two parameters, both of which are string slices that live at least as long as lifetime 'a. The function signature also tells Rust that the string slice returned from the function will live at least as long as lifetime 'a. In practice, it means that the lifetime of the reference returned by the longest function is the same as the smaller of the lifetimes of the references passed in. These constraints are what we want Rust to enforce. Remember, when we specify the lifetime parameters in this function signature, we’re not changing the lifetimes of any values passed in or returned. Rather, we’re specifying that the borrow checker should reject any values that don’t adhere to these constraints. Note that the longest function doesn’t need to know exactly how long x and y will live, only that some scope can be substituted for 'a that will satisfy this signature. When annotating lifetimes in functions, the annotations go in the function signature, not in the function body. Rust can analyze the code within the function without any help. However, when a function has references to or from code outside that function, it becomes almost impossible for Rust to figure out the lifetimes of the parameters or return values on its own. The lifetimes might be different each time the function is called. This is why we need to annotate the lifetimes manually.

When we pass concrete references to longest, the concrete lifetime that is substituted for 'a is the part of the scope of x that overlaps with the scope of y. In other words, the generic lifetime 'a will get the concrete lifetime that is equal to the smaller of the lifetimes of x and y. Because we’ve annotated the returned reference with the same lifetime parameter 'a, the returned reference will also be valid for the length of the smaller of the lifetimes of x and y.

Let’s look at how the lifetime annotations restrict the longest function by passing in references that have different concrete lifetimes.string1 is valid until the end of the outer scope, string2 is valid until the end of the inner scope, and result references something that is valid until the end of the inner scope. Run this code, and you’ll see that the borrow checker approves of this code; it will compile and print The longest string is long string is long.

Next, let’s try an example that shows that the lifetime of the reference in result must be the smaller lifetime of the two arguments. We’ll move the declaration of the result variable outside the inner scope but leave the assignment of the value to the result variable inside the scope with string2. Then we’ll move the println! that uses result outside the inner scope, after the inner scope has ended.The error shows that for result to be valid for the println! statement, string2 would need to be valid until the end of the outer scope. Rust knows this because we annotated the lifetimes of the function parameters and return values using the same lifetime parameter 'a.

As humans, we can look at this code and see that string1 is longer than string2 and therefore result will contain a reference to string1. Because string1 has not gone out of scope yet, a reference to string1 will still be valid for the println! statement. However, the compiler can’t see that the reference is valid in this case. We’ve told Rust that the lifetime of the reference returned by the longest function is the same as the smaller of the lifetimes of the references passed in. Therefore, the borrow checker disallows the code in Listing 10-24 as possibly having an invalid reference.

Try designing more experiments that vary the values and lifetimes of the references passed in to the longest function and how the returned reference is used. Make hypotheses about whether or not your experiments will pass the borrow checker before you compile; then check to see if you’re right!"/>


            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="25sp"
                android:fontFamily="serif"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="Thinking in Terms of Lifetimes"/>
            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="23sp"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="   The way in which you need to specify lifetime parameters depends on what your function is doing. For example, if we changed the implementation of the longest function to always return the first parameter rather than the longest string slice, we wouldn’t need to specify a lifetime on the y parameter. we’ve specified a lifetime parameter 'a for the parameter x and the return type, but not for the parameter y, because the lifetime of y does not have any relationship with the lifetime of x or the return value.

When returning a reference from a function, the lifetime parameter for the return type needs to match the lifetime parameter for one of the parameters. If the reference returned does not refer to one of the parameters, it must refer to a value created within this function, which would be a dangling reference because the value will go out of scope at the end of the function. The problem is that result goes out of scope and gets cleaned up at the end of the longest function. We’re also trying to return a reference to result from the function. There is no way we can specify lifetime parameters that would change the dangling reference, and Rust won’t let us create a dangling reference. In this case, the best fix would be to return an owned data type rather than a reference so the calling function is then responsible for cleaning up the value.

Ultimately, lifetime syntax is about connecting the lifetimes of various parameters and return values of functions. Once they’re connected, Rust has enough information to allow memory-safe operations and disallow operations that would create dangling pointers or otherwise violate memory safety."/>


            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="25sp"
                android:fontFamily="serif"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="Lifetime Annotations in Struct Definitions"/>
            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="23sp"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="   So far, we’ve only defined structs to hold owned types. It’s possible for structs to hold references, but in that case we would need to add a lifetime annotation on every reference in the struct’s definition. Listing 10-25 has a struct named ImportantExcerpt that holds a string slice. This struct has one field, part, that holds a string slice, which is a reference. As with generic data types, we declare the name of the generic lifetime parameter inside angle brackets after the name of the struct so we can use the lifetime parameter in the body of the struct definition. This annotation means an instance of ImportantExcerpt can’t outlive the reference it holds in its part field.

The main function here creates an instance of the ImportantExcerpt struct that holds a reference to the first sentence of the String owned by the variable novel. The data in novel exists before the ImportantExcerpt instance is created. In addition, novel doesn’t go out of scope until after the ImportantExcerpt goes out of scope, so the reference in the ImportantExcerpt instance is valid."/>





            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="25sp"
                android:fontFamily="serif"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="Summary"/>
            <TextView
                android:layout_width="match_parent"
                android:layout_height="wrap_content"
                android:textSize="23sp"
                android:justificationMode="inter_word"
                android:textColor="@color/black"
                android:text="  We covered a lot in this chapter! Now that you know about generic type parameters, traits and trait bounds, and generic lifetime parameters, you’re ready to write code without repetition that works in many different situations. Generic type parameters let you apply the code to different types. Traits and trait bounds ensure that even though the types are generic, they’ll have the behavior the code needs. You learned how to use lifetime annotations to ensure that this flexible code won’t have any dangling references. And all of this analysis happens at compile time, which doesn’t affect runtime performance!
Believe it or not, there is much more to learn on the topics we discussed in this chapter: Chapter 17 discusses trait objects, which are another way to use traits. There are also more complex scenarios involving lifetime annotations that you will only need in very advanced scenarios; for those, you should read the Rust Reference. But next, you’ll learn how to write tests in Rust so you can make sure your code is working the way it should."/>


        </LinearLayout>

    </ScrollView>


</RelativeLayout>